<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Numerical analysis, Dynamical systems / Analyse numérique</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Olivier</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Faugeras</surname></persName>
							<email>olivier.faugeras@inria.fr</email>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0001-8363-1550</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Inria</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2004, route des Lucioles -BP 93</addrLine>
									<postCode>06902</postCode>
									<settlement>Sophia Antipolis Cedex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anna</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
							<email>a.song19@imperial.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Haematopoietic Stem Cell Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Francis Crick Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Romain</forename><surname>Veltz</surname></persName>
							<email>romain.veltz@inria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Inria</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2004, route des Lucioles -BP 93</addrLine>
									<postCode>06902</postCode>
									<settlement>Sophia Antipolis Cedex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Numerical analysis, Dynamical systems / Analyse numérique</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">(electronic) : 1778-3569</idno>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">15CD84C449E41D345A1EA66032B554D6</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.5802/crmath.289</idno>
					<note type="submission">Manuscript received 19th October 2021, accepted 24th October 2021.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-03-07T09:37+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Systèmes dynamiques 2020 Mathematics Subject Classification. 37L10</term>
					<term>35B06</term>
					<term>35B32</term>
					<term>35G25</term>
					<term>37M20</term>
					<term>45B05</term>
					<term>45K05</term>
					<term>46E35</term>
					<term>47G20</term>
					<term>47H30</term>
					<term>65J15</term>
					<term>65R0</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We study a simplified model of the representation of colors in the primate primary cortical visual area V1. The model is described by an initial value problem related to a Hammerstein equation. The solutions to this problem represent the variation of the activity of populations of neurons in V1 as a function of space and color. The two space variables describe the spatial extent of the cortex while the two color variables describe the hue and the saturation represented at every location in the cortex. We prove the well-posedness of the initial value problem. We focus on its stationary, i.e. independent of time, and periodic in space solutions. We show that the model equation is equivariant with respect to the direct product G of the group of the Euclidean transformations of the planar lattice determined by the spatial periodicity and the group of color transformations, isomorphic to O(2), and study the equivariant bifurcations of its stationary solutions when some parameters in the model vary. Their variations may be caused by the consumption of drugs and the bifurcated solutions may represent visual hallucinations in space and color. Some of the bifurcated solutions can be determined by applying the Equivariant Branching Lemma (EBL) by determining the axial subgroups of G . These define bifurcated solutions which are invariant under the action of the corresponding axial subgroup. We compute analytically these solutions and illustrate them as color images. Using advanced methods of numerical bifurcation analysis we then explore the persistence and stability of these solutions when varying some parameters in the model. We conjecture that we can rely on the EBL to predict the existence of patterns that survive in large parameter domains but not to predict their stability. On our way we discover the existence of spatially localized stable patterns through the phenomenon of "snaking".</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Neural Fields are a useful mathematical formalism for representing the dynamics of cortical areas at a macroscopic level, see the reviews <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">24]</ref>. This formalism has been broadly used to account for the observed activity of the cortical visual area V1. V1 receives inputs from the retina through the Lateral Geniculate Nucleus (LGN). There is a massive feedback from V1 to the LGN. V1 also sends inputs to higher level cortical visual areas such as V2 and V4 and receives feedback signals from them. For a very accessible introduction to the various visual areas, the reader is referred to the book of David Hubel <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[35]</ref>, and to <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[38]</ref> for a more recent presentation.</p><p>Neural Fields models of V1 are sets of integro-differential equations whose solutions are meant to describe its spatio-temporal activity. The well-posedness of these equations has been studied in depth by various authors <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">65]</ref> with a special attention to the stationary solutions, i.e. those which do not depend upon time. These solutions, also called persistent states, are interesting because they appear to provide good models of memory holding tasks on the time scale of the second <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">42]</ref>. Moreover, they appear to resonate with the fascinating phenomenon of visual hallucinations and their relation with the functional architecture of the visual cortex <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">25]</ref>.</p><p>With no exception to our knowledge, all previous work in neural fields theory has not taken into account the chromatic aspects of visual perception. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57]</ref>, we introduced a neural field model for color perception to explore how the synergy of two antagonistic phenomena, simultaneous contrast and chromatic assimilation, could lead to a "color sensation".</p><p>In the present article, we address the questions of how this model can predict visual hallucinations and what are their spatial and chromatic structures. We are guided in this venture by our previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[64]</ref> and make good use of the theory of equivariant bifurcations.</p><p>It is structured as follows. In Section 2 we recall the neural field model described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57]</ref> and prove its well-posedness, Section 3 introduces the notion of stationary solutions and their bifurcations. Section 4 is dedicated to the computation of the spectrum of the linear operator in the neural field model. Section 5 describes the symmetries of the model and uses the equivariant branching lemma to predict the type of bifurcations at the primary bifurcation points and the shape of the bifurcated solutions, or planforms. <ref type="bibr">Section 6</ref> shows examples of such planforms. Section 7 goes away from this local analysis and explores numerically, thanks to the development of innovative software, a much larger volume of the set of stationary solutions to the neural field equations. We conclude in Section 8.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">The model</head><p>In this work we think of V1 as the closure of a regular domain, noted Ω s , s stands for space, of R 2 , in effect the open square (-l /2, l /2)×(-l /2, l /2), where l is a positive number which, for simplicity and without loss of generality, we take equal to 1, except for some of the numerical experiments presented in Section 7.</p><p>The visual cortex is organized into hypercolumns, groups of neurons sharing the same receptive field in the retina and coding for specific physical quantities such as edge orientation, spatial frequency, temporal frequency. These signals are mapped from the retina to V1 following an approximately log polar retinotopic transformation (see <ref type="bibr">Remark 22)</ref>. Unlike in the case of orientation, for which the existence of such hypercolumns in V1 is now well established <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[58]</ref>, the anatomical and physiological bases for a functional architecture encoding color are still debated. These bases are most likely connected to the presence of blobs <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">35]</ref>. Hence, in light of the promising findings reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">70]</ref> it is reasonable to assume in our work a hypercolumnar organisation of cells tuned to a continuum of colors. Our work also supposes the presence of long-range lateral connections between hypercolumns, in agreement with observations of <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[41]</ref> where horizontal connections tend to link blobs to blobs. Note that this visual information is stored in the cortex in three dimensions, i.e. the cortex has some thickness. We neglect in our work this thickness and consider only its spatial extent.</p><p>We now briefly recall the model described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57]</ref>. It is based on an opponent representation of colors such as Hering's opponent space <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref>. In this setting, a color is a pair c := (c 1 , c 2 ) of real C. R. Mathématique -0000, 1, n 0, 000-000 numbers which encode the chromaticity of the color <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> . Details are provided in Appendix A. The reader can think of c 1 as encoding the yellow-blue colors and c 2 as encoding the red-green colors in Hering's theory. What is important for us is that the set of chromaticities is symmetric w.r.t. the origin, i.e. if c = (c 1 , c 2 ) is a chromaticity, then -c = (-c 1 , -c 2 ) is also a chromaticity, called the opponent chromaticity or color of c. The set of chromaticities is therefore a bounded regular domain of R<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">2</ref> which is symmetric w.r.t. the origin, in effect the open disk D(0, c 0 ) centered at the origin and of radius c 0 , where c 0 is a positive number which we take without loss of generality and for convenience equal to 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Remark 1.</head><p>We implicitly assume that the topology of the chromaticity space is that of the Euclidean plane. This is only a coarse approximation. Note that the problem of defining a metric in color space is still open <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">61,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">69]</ref>.</p><p>For technical reasons, we consider only the open disk minus a radius, i.e. D(0, 1)\{[0, 1) × {0}}. We use polar coordinates to parametrize D(0, 1). A chromaticity is therefore represented by a pair (ρ, ϕ) with ρ ∈ (0, 1) and ϕ ∈ (0, 1), keeping in mind that the actual polar coordinates are (ρ, 2πϕ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Remark 2.</head><p>The elimination of the semi open radius [0, 1) × {0} from D(0, 1) is practically not important since the functions that we will manipulate, in particular the eigenfunctions of the operator W c , see below, will be smooth and therefore can be continuously extended to the closed disk D(0, 1).</p><p>The perceptual interpretation of ρ is the saturation of the color c while ϕ is its hue. The opponent chromaticity of (ρ, ϕ) is therefore (ρ, ϕ + 1 2 mod 1). The set Ω c of chromaticities is therefore the open square (0, 1) × (0, 1).</p><p>We define</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Ω = Ω s × Ω c</formula><p>to be the bounded domain, in effect the open rectangle of R<ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">4</ref> , encapsulating the spatial and chromatic coordinates that will be of interest in the sequel.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Connectivity kernel</head><p>Putting all this together, at each point (r, c) = (r 1 , r 2 , ρ, ϕ) of Ω, we consider a neural mass 2 whose average membrane potential is noted V (r, c, t ). It is a function defined on Ω × J , J being an interval of R containing 0. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57]</ref>, we assumed that the function V was the solution to an initial value problem<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">3</ref> related to a Hammerstein equation 4 which writes</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">τ ∂V ∂t (r, c, t ) = -V (r, c, t ) + w Υ (V (r, c, t )) + I ext (r, c, t ),<label>(1)</label></formula><p>together with the initial condition V (r, c, 0) = V 0 (r, c). This equation describes the time variation of the scalar function V (t ) defined on Ω starting from the initial condition V 0 . At each time t , V (t ) belongs to some functional space, in effect a Hilbert space F , that we describe in the next section.</p><p>We now discuss the various elements that appear in this equation.</p><p>τ is a time constant that defines the speed of the exponential decay toward the initial condition. Without loss of generality we can assume τ = 1.</p><p>Υ is a sigmoidal function mapping R to the open interval (0, 1). It is called the activation function, relating the values of the membrane potential V to the neuronal activity a (0 meaning quiet, 1 meaning highly active). It writes</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">Υ(x) = Sig(γx -ε) where Sig(x) = 1 1 + e -x .</formula><p>(</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">)<label>2</label></formula><p>ε is a parameter that allows us to shift the origin, γ controls the slope of the sigmoid at the (shifted) origin, it is often called the nonlinear gain. I ext is a function representing the input to the neural mass from different brain areas. In the remaining of this paper we take I ext = 0, i.e. we consider that area V 1 is isolated from the rest of the brain. This is clearly an approximation but allows us to do some mathematics and is a first step toward the analysis of the general case.</p><p>w is the connectivity kernel <ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">5</ref> . It models the influence of neighboring neural masses at (r , c ) on the neural mass at (r, c) as a (separable in space and color) linear superposition operation</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">w Υ V (r, ρ, ϕ, t ) = Ω s ×Ω c w(r, ρ, ϕ, r , ρ , ϕ )Υ V (r , ρ , ϕ , t ) ρ dρ dϕ dr ,<label>(3)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">with w(r, c, r , c ) = w s (r -r )w c (ρ, ρ , ϕ -ϕ ),</formula><p>where the index s stands for "space" and the index c stands for "chromaticity".</p><p>If w(r, c, r , c ) is positive (respectively negative) the neural mass at (r , c ) excites (respectively inhibits) the one at (r, c). The product of w s and w c is intended to model the antagonistic effects of color assimilation and contrast which are parts of the class of perceptual phenomena called chromatic interactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[66]</ref>.</p><p>w s is a "classical" two-dimensional "Mexican hat" function, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref>-Left, which we write as the difference of two circularly symmetric Gaussians centered at 0:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">w s (r ) = µ s e -r 2 2 /2α 2 s -ν s e -r 2 2 /2β 2 s , (<label>4</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">)</formula><p>where 2 is the usual Euclidean L 2 norm in R 2 . Biology dictates that α s , β s are very small w.r.t. 1, the size of Ω s . This indicates that our model only takes into account the neural connections which are local to the visual area V1 and take place within the gray matter while it is known that different visual areas communicate through the fiber bundles (in the biological sense) forming part of the white matter. This would be part of the term I ext in (1) which we have taken to be equal to 0.</p><p>If w s (0) &gt; 0, i.e. if µ s &gt; ν s , the neural masses at r such that rr 2 is small enough excite the neural mass at r , and if α s &lt; β s those sufficiently far away inhibit it.</p><p>We furthermore assume</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">Ω s w s (r ) dr = 0,<label>(5)</label></formula><p>i.e. that the spatial excitation and inhibition are balanced. This is both compatible with some biological evidence (balanced networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref>) and mathematically convenient.</p><p>The function w c is separable in polar coordinates,</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">w c (ρ, ρ , ϕ) = w c,m (ρ, ρ )w c,a (ϕ),<label>(6)</label></formula><p>with</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">w c,m (ρ, ρ ) = e -ξ c |ρ 2 -ρ 2 | ,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">w c,a (ϕ) = µ c e -2πα c |(ϕ-1 2 mod 1)-1 2 | -ν c e -2πβ c |(ϕ mod 1)-1 2 | (8)</formula><p>The parameters ξ c , µ c , ν c , α c and β c are positive and such that w c,a (c, c ) is positive if c is close to c and negative if c is close to -c, i.e. in terms of polar coordinates if ρ is close to ρ and either ϕ is close to ϕ or ϕ is close to ϕ + 1 2 mod 1. A plot of the 1-periodic function w c,a is shown in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>. </p><formula xml:id="formula_12">w c,m ( , ) = e -ξ c | -| ,<label>(9)</label></formula><p>and the measure ρ dρ on (0, 1) is equal to 1  2 d . In what follows we ignore the factor 1 2 . A chromaticity is therefore represented by a pair ( , ϕ), , ϕ ∈ (0, 1).</p><p>The product w of w s and w c behaves as a function of r, r , c, c as shown in Table <ref type="table">1</ref> adapted from <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57]</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">Table 1. Sign of the connectivity kernel w w s (r -r )w c ( , , ϕ -ϕ ) c close to c c close to -c r close to r &gt; 0 &lt; 0 r far from r &lt; 0 &gt; 0</formula><p>As pointed out in this paper, this is in qualitative agreement with the nonlinear behaviour of color shifts found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">44]</ref>.</p><p>Note that by definition of w s and w c the function w is symmetric w.r.t. r and r , and c and c , respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Choice of the appropriate functional space F and well-posedness of (1)</head><p>Our choice of F is guided by three criteria:</p><p>(1) The well-posedness of the problem, (2) Its biological relevance, (3) Its suitability for numerical computations.</p><p>The choice of a Hilbert space is appealing and a natural choice is F = L 2 (Ω). As argued in <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[65]</ref>, this unfortunately allows the membrane potential to be singular since for example the function (r, c) → r -1/2 2 ∈ L 2 (Ω). It is desirable that the average membrane potential stays bounded on the cortex and a way to achieve this is to allow for more spatial and chromatic regularity by assuming that (r, c) → V (r, c) is differentiable almost everywhere.</p><p>The choice of the Sobolev space F = W m,2 , is convenient for two reasons. First it is a Hilbert space endowed with the usual inner product:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">〈V 1 ,V 2 〉 F = m |α|=0 〈D α V 1 , D α V 2 〉 L 2 (Ω) ∀ V 1 , V 2 ∈ F (<label>10</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_15">)</formula><p>where the multi-index α is a sequence α = (α 1 , α 2 , α 3 , α 4 ) of 4 integers and |α| = 4 i =1 α i , and the symbol D α represents a partial derivative, e.g.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">D α V = ∂ α 1 +•••+α 4 ∂r α 1 1 ∂r α 2 2 ∂ α 3 ∂ϕ α 4 V</formula><p>The second reason is that, because the boundary of Ω is sufficiently regular (it satisfies the coneproperty <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>), F is a commutative Banach algebra for pointwise multiplication <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>[Chapter V, Theorem 5.23]. This is necessary in the upcoming bifurcation analysis in order to apply the Equivariant Branching Lemma, see Theorem 18, for which we require some smoothness of w.</p><p>Remark 5. The reader probably wonders what is the value of m. In order to have the Banach algebra property, we need to have 2m &gt; d , d being the dimension of Ω, i.e. 4. Hence the smallest possible value of m is 3. But in Section 7 we assume that Ω c is one-dimensional making d equal to 3 and the smallest possible value of m is equal to 2 in this case.</p><p>We next define the operator W as acting on L 2 (Ω) as follows. Let U ∈ L 2 (Ω), we define <ref type="figure">r ,</ref><ref type="figure">c</ref> ) dr dc Remark 6. Remember that the measure dc is in effect equal to 1  2 d dϕ .</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">W •U (r, c) := w U (r, c) = Ω w s (r -r )w c (c, c )U (</formula><p>It is clear that this is well defined and we have the following proposition.</p><p>Proposition 7. The operator W maps L 2 (Ω) to F and hence F to F .</p><p>Proof. The proof follows from Proposition 2.3 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[65]</ref>.</p><p>We also have the following Proposition about the solutions to (1).</p><p>Proposition 8. For each V 0 ∈ F there exists a unique solution in C (R + , F ) to the following Cauchy problem</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">dV dt = -V + W • Υ(V ) V (0) = V 0 , (<label>11</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_19">)</formula><p>where the function s is defined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>.</p><p>Proof. The proof is a an immediate consequence of Proposition 2.5 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[65]</ref>.</p><p>C. R. Mathématique -0000, 1, n 0, 000-000</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Stationary solutions and bifurcations thereof</head><p>In this paper, we focus on the stationary (independent of time) solutions to <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>, the steadystates. As mentioned before they are important because they are thought to be good models of the memory holding tasks on the timescale of the second as demonstrated experimentally on primates <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">42]</ref>. These solutions may change drastically when some of the parameters such as γ and ε in (2), µ s , ν s , α s , β s in (4), ξ c in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, and µ c , ν c , α c , β c in (8) vary. In effect, we will concentrate on the first parameter, the nonlinear gain γ, which is important in determining the relation between neuronal activity (a number between 0 and 1) and the associated membrane potential V . It is known that the ingestion of drugs such as LSD and marijuana a) can change this relation and b) can trigger hallucinatory patterns <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">54]</ref>. It is therefore very much worth our efforts to investigate if, when varying the parameter γ, stationary solutions to <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> do bifurcate and if the bifurcated solutions resemble some of the known visual illusions.</p><p>To summarize, we are going to study the bifurcations when γ varies of the solutions to the equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">F (V, γ) = 0, (<label>12</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">)</formula><p>where the operator F is defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">F def. = W m,2 (Ω) × R -→ L 2 (Ω) (V, γ) -→ -V + W • Υ (V ) . (<label>13</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_23">)</formula><p>In order to achieve such a task, we need to determine the spectrum of the operator W and the symmetry properties of the operator F with respect to some groups of transformations of Ω. We describe the spectrum of W in Section 4 and the symmetry properties of F in Section 5.</p><p>It is natural at this point to introduce the two operators W s and W c acting on L 2 (Ω) associated to the functions w s of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">4</ref>) and w c of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">6</ref>) as follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">W s •U (r, c) = Ω s w s (r -r )U (r , c) dr and W c •U (r, , ϕ) = Ω c w c ( , ϕ, , ϕ )U (r, , ϕ ) d dϕ .</formula><p>The separability of the function w in the space and color variables is reflected in the notation</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">W = W c ⊗ W s . Fubini's Theorem dictates that W is also equal to W s ⊗ W c .</formula><p>Similarly the separability of the function w c as the product of w c,m in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> for the magnitude and w c,a in (8) for the angle implies that <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> where the convolution in the right hand side of the definition of W c,a is a periodic convolution.</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">W c is itself separable, W c = W c,m ⊗ W c,a = W c,a ⊗ W c,m : W c,m •U (r, , ϕ) = 1 0 w c,m ( , )U (r, , ϕ) d and W c,a •U (r, , ϕ) = 1 0 w c,a (ϕ -ϕ )U (r, , ϕ ) dϕ</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">The spectrum of W in L 2 (Ω)</head><p>The reader can verify that, given the symmetry properties of the functions w c and w s , the operator W is symmetric in L 2 (Ω), i.e. satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">〈U 1 , W •U 2 〉 L 2 (Ω) = 〈W •U 1 , U 2 〉 L 2 (Ω) .</formula><p>Another important property of W is that it is compact, i.e. given any bounded sequence (U n ) n≥0 of functions in L 2 (Ω) the sequence (W • U n ) n≥0 contains a converging subsequence for the L 2 (Ω) norm. This is a direct consequence of Lemma 2.4 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[65]</ref>.</p><p>A consequence of the fact that W is compact is that its spectrum is compact and at most countable. Moreover each point in the spectrum, except perhaps 0, is isolated. All the non zero elements of the spectrum are eigenvalues and all eigenvalues are real since W is symmetric.</p><p>Since w is separable in space and color, the spectrum of W is defined by the spectra of W s and W c : the eigenvalues are the product of those of each operator and the eigenfunctions are separable in space and color, being the products of those of W s and W c .</p><p>4.1. The spectrum of W s in L 2 (Ω s )</p><p>Because we are studying the symmetry-breaking steady-state bifurcations of the solutions to our model, we know from previous work on heat-conduction in fluids <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> or on visual hallucinations <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> that this leads to the formation of spatially periodic patterns.</p><p>This brings into play the lattice L generated by the two vectors k 1 and k 2 where (k 1 , k 2 ) is the canonical basis of R 2 and commands that we quotient R 2 by L thus obtaining the 2-torus T 2 = R 2 /L . The dual lattice L * is also generated by the two vectors k 1 and k 2 .</p><p>We thus make the following assumption about the solutions to equations (1) which is inspired by biology with the advantage that it simplifies the mathematics: Hypothesis 9. The biologically relevant solutions to (1) are L -periodic i.e. satisfy</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">V (r + l , c, t ) = V (r, c, t ) ∀ l ∈ L</formula><p>We now work on the Hilbert space L 2 (T 2 ) of L -periodic functions with the same inner product as before. We note W s the operator W s restricted to this space i.e. defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">W s • V (r ) = Ω s w s r -r mod L V (r )dr := T 2 w s (r -r )V (r )dr ∀ r ∈ Ω s ,</formula><p>Note that the spatial convolution in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">3</ref>) is now a periodic convolution. W s is clearly a symmetric compact operator on L 2 (T 2 ).</p><p>It is easy to characterize the spectrum of W s :</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">Proposition 10. The eigenvalues λ s m,n , m, n ∈ Z, of W s ∈ L 2 (T 2</formula><p>) are the (real) Fourier coefficients of the L -periodic even function w s :</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">λ s m,n = T 2 w s (r ) cos 2π〈k m,n , r 〉 dr, where k m,n := mk 1 + nk 2 .</formula><p>Because w s is even, so is the sequence of eigenvalues: λ s m,n = λ s -m,-n , m, n ∈ Z, and, because of (5), λ s 0,0 = 0.Given an eigenvalue λ s m,n the corresponding eigenspace is generated by the functions: cos 2π〈k p,q , r 〉 and sin 2π〈k p,q , r 〉, for all (p, q) such that λ s p,q = λ s m,n .</p><p>Proof. This follows for example from the fact that W s is diagonalized by the Fourier Transform.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Spectrum of W c in L 2 (Ω c )</head><p>Define the operator τ c acting on the ϕ-periodic functions of period 1 as</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">τ c • u( , ϕ) = u( , -ϕ mod 1) (<label>15</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_33">)</formula><p>τ c is the reflection wrt the c 1 axis in Ω c and we have the following Proposition.</p><p>C. R. Mathématique -0000, 1, n 0, 000-000</p><p>Proposition 11. The linear operator W c on L 2 (Ω c ) is symmetric and compact, it commutes with the operator τ c defined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>.</p><p>Proof. Obvious from the definitions.</p><p>From this we have Corollary 12. The spectrum of W c is real and at most countable. The eigenfunctions are separable w.r.t. , ϕ.</p><p>Proof. The first assertion follows from the symmetry and compactness of W c . The second follows from the definitions ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">6</ref>)- <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>.</p><p>It remains to characterize the eigenfunctions and eigenvalues.</p><p>Proposition 13. The eigenspaces of W c,a are generated by the functions sin 2πnϕ and cos 2πnϕ, n ∈ N. The corresponding eigenvalues are the (real) Fourier coefficients of the 1-periodic even function given by (8) of index n.</p><p>Proof. This follows immediatly from the fact that the operator W c,a is a 1-periodic convolution and the 1-periodic function</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">µ c e -2πα c |(ϕ-1 2 mod 1)-1 2 | -ν c e -2πβ c |ϕ mod 1)-1 2 | is even.</formula><p>Regarding W c,m , we have the following Proposition.</p><p>Proposition 14. The eigenspaces of W c,m corresponding to the non zero eigenvalues are onedimensional. Its kernel is reduced to the null function, i.e. W c,m is injective. The eigenvalues λ c n , n ∈ N, are obtained from the countable solutions x n to the transcendental equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">tan x = 2ξ c x x 2 -ξ 2 c , x &gt; 0, (<label>16</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_36">)</formula><p>from the relation</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">λ c n = ξ c ξ 2 c + x 2 n (<label>17</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_38">)</formula><p>The eigenfunction e c,m λ n corresponding to the eigenvalue λ n = 0 is given by e c,m</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">λ n ( ) = ξ c sin x n + x n cos x n . (<label>18</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_40">)</formula><p>Proof. We have, according to ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_12">9</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">W c,m • u( ) = 1 0 e -ξ c | -| u( ) d . Deriving twice w.r.t. W c,m • u (2) ( ) = ξ 2 c W c,m • u( ) -ξ c u(</formula><p>), so that if u is an eigenfunction corresponding to the eigenvalue λ c we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">λ c u (2) ( ) = ξ c ξ c λ c -1 u( ), which shows that if λ c = 0, u = 0. If λ c = 0 we define K := ξ c ξ c -1 λ c . The eigenfunctions are solutions to u (2) ( ) = K u( )<label>(19)</label></formula><p>which are of the form u( ); = ae K + be -K for some constants a and b, real or complex. λ c , a and b are determined by writing that the function u thus defined is indeed an eigenfunction of W c,m corresponding to the eigenvalue λ c . It can be verified that if K ≥ 0, i.e. if λ c ≥ 1 ξ c , there are no solutions. Hence we must assume λ c &lt; 1 ξ c and hence K &lt; 0. The solutions to <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref> write</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">u( ) = a sin -K + b cos -K<label>(20)</label></formula><p>A symbolic computation system shows that</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">W c,m • u( ) = λ c u( ) + λ c 2ξ c e ξ c e -ξ c -a -K cos -K + ξ c sin -K + b -K sin -K -ξ c cos -K +e -ξ c a -K -bξ c .</formula><p>The two conditions</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">-a -K cos -K + ξ c sin -K + b -K sin -K -ξ c cos -K = 0, and a -K -bξ c = 0 (<label>21</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_46">)</formula><p>are necessary and sufficient to guarantee that W c,m • u( ) = λ c u( ) for all 0 &lt; &lt; 1. Since a and b are not both equal to 0 (otherwise u = 0 and hence λ c = 0) we must have</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">2ξ c -K cos -K + (ξ 2 c + K ) sin -K = 0, which is equivalent to tan -K = - 2ξ c -K ξ 2 c + K Letting x = -K , the eigenvalues are found by solving for x &gt; 0 the equation tan x = 2ξ c x x 2 -ξ 2 c .</formula><p>For each value of x, the corresponding value of λ c is found to be</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">λ c = ξ c ξ 2 c + x 2 The function x → 2ξ c x x 2 -ξ 2 c</formula><p>decreases monotonically from +∞ for x = ξ + c to 0 when x → +∞. The corresponding curve therfore intersects the curve representing the π-periodic function x → tan x at a countable number of points x n , n ≥ 0, yielding the eigenvalues λ c n of W c,m . According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(20)</ref> and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_45">21</ref>) the corresponding eigenfunction is</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">e c,m λ c n ( ) = ξ c sin x n + x n cos x n .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Symmetries of the model and equivariant bifurcations of the solutions</head><p>It follows from ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">5</ref>) that V = 0 is a solution to ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_20">12</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_22">13</ref>) for all values of γ. We are interested in the problem of determining how this solution bifurcates when γ increases, while allowing us to change somewhat the value of the threshold ε in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>.</p><p>Because of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_20">12</ref>), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_22">13</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">2</ref>) we have the Jacobian of F with respect to V at (0, γ) is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">dF V (0, γ) = -Id +γ Sig (-ε)W,</formula><p>Let λ p be the largest positive eigenvalue of W . When one increases γ from 0 to γ p def.</p><p>= 1/(λ p Sig(-ε)) the solution V = 0 (may) bifurcates to another solution.</p><p>We investigate the properties of the operator F defined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> under the action of the Euclidean group E (2) restricted to the lattice L defined at the beginning of Section 4.1 for the spatial part, and the group O(2) for the color part. This last group is generated by the rotations R c ϕ c acting on the ϕ angle by ϕ → ϕ + ϕ c mod 1 and the reflection τ c : ϕ → -ϕ mod 1. An element ψ of this group is of the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">ψ = R c ϕ c τ m c , m ∈ {0, 1}.<label>(22)</label></formula><p>C. R. Mathématique -0000, 1, n 0, 000-000</p><p>The action of E (2) on the space of L -periodic functions is best understood by considering separately the translations and the rotations. Since the translations of R 2 leave the set of Lperiodic functions invariant and translations in L fix all L -periodic functions, the effective action of the group of translations of R 2 is as the 2-torus T 2 = R 2 /L which is compact. For the rotations, recall that the holohedry H of the lattice L is the largest subgroup of O(2) that leaves L invariant. In the case of a square lattice H = D 4 is the dihedral group of the symmetries of the square. It follows that the largest subgroup of E (2) that leaves L invariant is the compact semidirect sum E (L ) := D 4 +T 2 . Therefore, we are interested in the action on F of the compact group G = E (L ) × O <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>. We have the following Proposition.</p><p>Proposition 15. The operator F defined in (13) is equivariant w.r.t. the action of the group G .</p><p>Proof. The action of the element g = ( , ψ) ∈ G on F , with ψ given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(22)</ref>, is defined as follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">g • F (V, γ)(r, , ϕ) = F (V, γ)( -1 r, , (-1) m (ϕ -ϕ c )), m ∈ {0, 1},</formula><p>and, because of Proposition 11, the reader can verify that F is equivariant w.r.t. the action of G , i.e. that we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">g • F (V, γ)(r, c) = F (g • V, γ)(r, c) ∀ g ∈ G . (<label>23</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_54">)</formula><p>At this point, branches of planforms are usually obtained by applying the equivariant branching lemma <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">60]</ref> as follows. The kernel V of dF (0, γ p ) is G -invariant. We fix an isotropy subgroup Σ of G (i.e. for which there exists v 0 ∈ V such that g • v 0 = v 0 for all g ∈ Σ) and compute the dimension of the fixed point subspace Fix V (Σ) of V associated with Σ where</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">Fix V (Σ) := {v ∈ V , σ • v = v, ∀ σ ∈ Σ} .</formula><p>The equivariant branching lemma states that if Σ is an axial subgroup of G, i.e. such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">dim Fix V (Σ) = 1,<label>(24)</label></formula><p>then generically, there is a branch of steady-state solutions to (1) with symmetries Σ. The genericity condition requires that the eigenvalue that goes through 0 does so with nonzero speed and that some components of the Taylor expansion of F are non zero. We characterize the isotropy subgroups of G and the corresponding fixed point subspaces in the following Proposition. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">2</ref>) fall in two classes: those which do not contain the color reflection τ c are those of H := E (L ) × SO <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>, and those that do contain τ c . In the first case the corresponding fixed subspaces are those of Σ as a subgroup of H . In the second case the fixed subspaces are those of Σ ∩ H projected on V 1 along V -1 , the eigenspaces of τ c corresponding to the eigenvalues 1 and -1, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proposition 16. The isotropy subgroups</head><formula xml:id="formula_57">Σ of G = E (L ) × O(</formula><p>Proof. If we restrict the color group O(2) to SO(2), i.e. if we only consider the action of the color rotations, our symmetry group is the same as for the equivariant Hopf bifurcation with E (L ) symmetry <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">56]</ref>. We note that the fixed point subspaces have even dimension since SO <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> commutes with E (L ) and all real finite dimensional non trivial representation of SO(2) are of even dimension. All fixed point subspaces of V for the action of H are therefore of even dimension.</p><p>If we now extend SO <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> to O(2), i.e. H to G , given an isotropy subroup Σ of G , either it is an isotropy subgroup of H and we are done, or it is not and the color reflection operator τ c is not reduced to the identity on Fix V (Σ). But τ c is a projector. It has therefore two eigenspaces V ±1 corresponding to its eigenvalues ±1 and V is the direct sum of the corresponding eigenspaces.</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">Let v ∈ Fix V (Σ ∩ H ). We write v = v 1 + v -1 where v ±1 ∈ V ±1 . We have τ c • v = τ c • v 1 + τ c • v -1 = v 1 -v -1 ,<label>(25)</label></formula><p>so that the projection p 1 (Fix</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">V (Σ ∩ H )) of Fix V (Σ ∩ H ) on V 1 along V -1 is included in Fix V (Σ). Conversely, let v ∈ Fix V (Σ). The condition v ∈ Fix V (Σ) and (25) impose τ c •v = v, i.e. τ c •v -1 = 0, i.e. v -1 = 0. so that v = v 1 and Fix V (Σ) ⊂ p 1 (Fix V (Σ ∩ H )). Remark 17. In fact, writing O(2) = SO(2) ⊕ Z 2 , with Z 2 = {1, -1} the (closed) subgroups of O(2)</formula><p>fall in three classes <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[36]</ref> I: Closed subgroups of SO <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>. II: Closed subgroups containing -1: they are of the form Σ ⊕ Z 2 , Σ a subgroup of SO <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>. III: Closed subgroups of O(2) which are not a subgroup of SO(2) and do not contain -1.</p><p>In Proposition 16 we considered only the subgroups of O(2) of class I and II. As shown in, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr">Chapter 13,</ref><ref type="bibr">p</ref>. 131], those subgroups Σ are determined by pairs K ⊂ H of subgroups of SO <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> such that K has index 2 in H , see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[46]</ref>. If p : SO(2) ⊕ Z 2 → SO(2), p(ψ) = det(ψ)ψ, is the projection, then H = p(Σ) is isomorphic to Σ and Σ = K ∪ ψK for any -ψ ∈ H \K . It is not difficult to list all such pairs (K , H ) using the results in <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[45]</ref>. None of them produces a subgroup of E (L )×O(2) with a nonzero fixed subspace, basically because the color rotations act on V by multiplications with a magnitude 1 complex exponential.</p><p>Since V is G -invariant and G is compact, we can write V as a direct sum of G -irreducible subspaces (subspaces such that their only G -invariant subspaces are 0 or the whole subspace), see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[30,</ref><ref type="bibr">Theorem 1.22]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">V = V 1 ⊕ • • • ⊕ V k . It follows easily that Fix V (Σ) = Fix V 1 (Σ) ⊕ • • • ⊕ Fix V k (Σ).</formula><p>Hence if dim(Fix V (Σ)) = 1 then Fix V (Σ) = Fix V j (Σ) for some j so that the first step in classifying the planforms associated with a fixed lattice L is to enumerate each G -irreducible subspace of V . Moreover V j is of the form V s j ×V c j where V s j is an eigenspace of W s irreducible under the action of E (L ) and V c j is an eigenspace of W c irreducible under the action of O(2). This has been worked out in the case of E (L ) by several authors including <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref>. Dropping the upper index j for simplicity, the irreducible representations of V s must be of the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">V s = V s K 1 ⊕ • • • ⊕ V s K ρ ,</formula><p>where V K j = Vect ze 2πi 〈K j ,r 〉 + c.c., z ∈ C , j = 1, . . . , k, where c.c. means "complex conjuguate". K 1 , . . . , K k are elements of L * and the set {±K 1 , . . . , ±K k } is an orbit in L * of the holohedry D 4 . As proved in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref>, there exists only one such representation of dimension 4 and a countable number of them of dimension 8 if we add the further constraint that they have to be translation free. A representation is translation free if there are no (nontrivial) translations in E (L ) that act trivially on <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(28)</ref>. This requirement ensures that we have found the finest lattice, L , that supports the neutral modes (28) <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref>.</p><p>The first one corresponds to</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">K 1 = k 1 K 2 = k 2 ,<label>(26)</label></formula><p>the second to</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">       K 1 = uk 1 + vk 2 K 2 = -vk 1 + uk 2 K 3 = vk 1 + uk 2 K 4 = -uk 1 + vk 2 ,<label>(27)</label></formula><p>C. R. Mathématique -0000, 1, n 0, 000-000</p><p>where u and v are relatively prime strictly positive integers such that u + v is odd. With our notations, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">V =      u(r, , ϕ) u(r, , ϕ) = k j =1</formula><p>z j e 2πi 〈K j , r 〉 e 2πi nϕ e c,m ( ) + w j e -2πi 〈K j , r 〉 e 2πi nϕ e c,m ( ) + c.c.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">z j , w j ∈ C      , k = 2, 4,<label>(28)</label></formula><p>which is isomorphic to C 2k by u → (z, w) := (z 1 , . . . , z k , w 1 , . . . , w k ).</p><p>If we now consider an isotropy subgroup Σ of H , such that dim Fix V (Σ) = 2, Proposition 7.2 in <ref type="bibr">[31,</ref> Chapter XVI] asserts that Σ is a twisted group, i.e. there is a pair of subgroups K ⊂ G of E (L ) and a unique homomorphism Θ : G → SO <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_66">such that Σ = G Θ := {(g , Θ(g )) ∈ E (L )×SO(2), g ∈ G}.</formula><p>K is the kernel of Θ: K = ker Θ. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22,</ref><ref type="bibr">Table 16</ref> on p. 157 and Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">21</ref> on p. 160] the authors compute all such subgroups and their fixed point subspaces. Using Proposition 16 we can obtain the corresponding subgroups of G and their corresponding fixed point subspaces.</p><p>In detail, D 4 is generated by the π/2 rotation, noted R s π/2 and the reflection, noted τ r 1 through the r 1 -axis. The action of E (L ) on V induces an action on C 2k . The reader will verify that this action is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">R s π/2 • (z, w) = (z 2 , w 1 , w 2 , z 1 ) k = 2 (z 2 , w 1 , w 2 , z 1 , z 4 , w 3 , w 4 , z 3 ) k = 4,<label>(29)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">τ r 1 • (z, w) = (z 1 , w 2 , w 1 , z 2 ) k = 2 (w 4 , w 3 , w 2 , w 1 , z 4 , z 3 , z 2 , z 1 ) k = 4.<label>(30)</label></formula><p>Similarly, for the action of O( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">2</ref>), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">R c ϕ c • (z, w) = e 2πi nϕ c (z, w), k = 2, 4<label>(31)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">τ c • (z, w) = (w, z), k = 2, 4.<label>(32)</label></formula><p>Writing (z j , w j ) = 1 2 (z j + w j , z j + w j ) + 1 2 (z jw j , -z j + w j ), j = 1, . . . , k,</p><p>shows that the projection of (z, w) on V 1 is 1 2 (z + w, z + w). The results in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref> allow us to determine all the axial subgroups of G in dimension 4 (because of <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[56]</ref>) and only some of them in dimension 8. They are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref> where we have noted v d the vector 1  2 (k 1 + k 2 ), e s the identity of D 4 and e c the identity of O(2). We can now apply the equivariant branching lemma. In detail, we have the following Theorem.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref>, there exists a unique branch of solutions to F (V, γ n ) = 0 emanating from (0, γ n ) where the symmetry of the solution is Σ. Moreover each of these branches stems from a pitchfork bifurcation.</p><p>Proof. The proof is a direct application of [15, Theorem 2.3.2] around γ = γ n . From Section 2.2 the mapping F is smooth. Its Jacobian at V = 0 is the linear operator</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">dF V (0, γ n ) = -Id +γ n Sig (-ε)W,</formula><p>where Sig is defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>. As W m,2 (Ω) is compactly included in L 2 (Ω) and W ∈ L (L 2 (Ω)) is compact, it follows that W is compact from W m,2 (Ω) to L 2 (Ω). This implies that dF V (0, γ n ) is a Fredholm operator with index 0.  <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">2</ref>)) is noted e s (respectively e c ). The vector v d is equal to 1  </p><formula xml:id="formula_72">2 (k 1 + k 2 ). Generators of G θ Σ := p 1 Fix G Θ dim V = 4 SR ((-e s , 0), 0), ((e s , 1 2 ), R c<label>1 2</label></formula><p>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">z 1 = w 1 real, z 2 = w 2 = 0 S2 ((R s π/2 , 0</formula><p>), e c ), ((τ r 1 , 0), e c ), ((e s , v d ), R c )</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">((R s π/2 , 0), τ c ), ((τ r 1 , 0), τ c ), ((e s , v d ), R c 1 2 τ c ) z 1 = z 2 = w 1 = w 2 , z 1 real dim V = 8 S2 u,v ((R s π/2 , 0), e c ), ((τ r 1 , 0), e c ), ((e s , v d ), R c<label>1 2</label></formula><p>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">((R s π/2 , 0), τ c ), ((τ r 1 , 0), τ c ), ((e s , v d ), R c 1 2 τ c ) z 1 = z 2 = z 3 = z 4 , w = z, z 1 real S4 u,v ((R s π/2 , 0), e c ), ((τ r 1 , v d ), e c ), ((e s , v d ), R c<label>1 2</label></formula><p>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">((R s π/2 , 0), τ c ), ((τ r 1 , v d ), τ c ), ((e s , v d ), R c 1 2 τ c ) z 1 = z 2 = -z 3 = -z 4 , w = z, z 1 real</formula><p>From the previous linear analysis, 0 is an isolated eigenvalue of dF V (0, γ n ) ∈ L (L 2 (Ω)) with finite multiplicity.</p><p>Let us denote the reduced equation by f (v, γ) = 0, v ∈ V : it is given by the Lyapunov-Schmidt method, see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref>. It remains to show that d 2 vγ f (0, 0) = 0 to complete the proof of the generic existence/uniqueness of a bifurcating branch.</p><p>We restrict ourselves to the case ε = 0 for which Sig (2) (0) = 0. The methods described in e.g. [29, Chapter VII, p. 295], allow us to find, using the fact that dF V is hermitian, that d 2 vγ f (0, 0) = ζ, ∂ γ dF (0, 0) • ζ where ζ ∈ V is of unit norm. A direct computation gives d 2  vγ f (0, 0) = 1 γ n = 0. The type of bifurcation that occurs can be determined by applying, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr">Theorem 2.3.2]</ref>. For each of the four subgroups G θ of G which appear in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref> we verify (using the relation</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">τ c R c 1 2 = R c 1 2</formula><p>τ c ) that the element g 0 := ((e s , 0), R c</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">1 2</formula><p>) is in the normalizer N (G θ ) of G θ since it satisfies g 0 g g -1 0 = g for all generators of G θ glven in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref> and acts as -1 on p 1 Fix(G θ ) .</p><p>This Theorem allows us to discover a specific class of planforms, i.e. some of those satisfying <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(24)</ref>. In general and generically, there may exist solutions such that dim(Fix V (Σ)) &gt; 1. Our approach here will not allow us to find these. Note however that the assumption <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(24)</ref> is the most commonly made. Exceptions to this can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Examples of planforms</head><p>Using Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref> and<ref type="table">(</ref> <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28)</ref>, it is easy to write down the analytical expressions of the four types of planforms. In the case where dim V = 4, we have SR(r, , ϕ) = cos 2πr 1 e c,m ( ) cos(2πnϕ), <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(33)</ref> and</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">S2(r, , ϕ) = (cos 2πr 1 + cos 2πr 2 ) e c,m ( ) cos(2πnϕ). (<label>34</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_80">)</formula><p>The first type of planform is called standing rolls (SR) or stripes, the second type is called spots. We show in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref> an example of standing rolls (or stripes) described by equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(33)</ref> in cortical and retinal coordinates, respectively. The relation between cortical and retinal coordinates C. R. Mathématique -0000, 1, n 0, 000-000  is discussed in Remark 22. Similarly we show in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref> an example of spots described by equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(34)</ref>. The details of the function e c,m and the value of the integer n are given in Remark 20 below.</p><p>In the case dim V = 8 we have the two families of planforms</p><formula xml:id="formula_81">S2 u,v (r, , ϕ) = cos 2π(ur 1 + vr 2 ) + cos 2π(-vr 1 + ur 2 )</formula><p>+ cos 2π(vr 1 + ur 2 ) + cos 2π(-ur 1 + vr 2 ) e c,m ( ) cos(2πnϕ), <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(35)</ref> and</p><formula xml:id="formula_82">S4 u,v (r, , ϕ) = cos 2π(ur 1 + vr 2 ) + cos 2π(-vr 1 + ur 2 )</formula><p>cos 2π(vr 1 + ur 2 )cos 2π(-ur 1 + vr 2 ) e c,m ( ) cos(2πnϕ), <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(36)</ref> where u and v are relatively prime strictly positive integers such that u + v is odd. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref> shows an example of a planform S2 1,2 and Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref> shows an example of a planform S4 3,2 . As above, the details of the function e c,m and the value of the integer n are given in Remark 20 below.  Remark 19. To determine the color represented at cortical location (r 1 , r 2 ), and produce the images in Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>, we compute c max (r 1 , r 2 ) = argmax ,ϕ Υ V eq (r 1 , r 2 , , ϕ) ∈ Ω c (corresponding to the maximum activity of the neural mass with spatial coordinates (r 1 , r 2 )), V eq ∈ {SR, S2, S2 u,v , S4 u,v }, and define the Luminance to be the corresponding activity level Υ V eq (r 1 , r 2 , c max (r 1 , r 2 )) . In case there are several argmax, we arbitrarily select one of them. At each cortical location (r 1 , r 2 ) we display the color using the HSL color coordinates, see Appendix A and <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[37]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_83">H = 2πϕ S = L = Υ V eq (r 1 , r 2 , c max (r 1 , r 2 ))</formula><p>Remark 20. In Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>the value of n in Proposition 13 is equal to 6. The value of ξ c in Proposition 14 is equal to 2 and x n is the fourth strictly positive root of equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_35">16</ref>). This implies that the product e h,m ( ) cos(2πnϕ) has several minima and maxima so that there are several values of ( , ϕ) where the maximum of Υ(SR(r, , ϕ))(respectively of Υ(S2(r, , ϕ)),</p><p>C. R. Mathématique -0000, 1, n 0, 000-000 Υ(S2 u,v (r, , ϕ)) or Υ(S4 u,v (r, , ϕ))) with respect to ( , ϕ) is reached. As mentioned in Remark 19 and in Section 7.1 we have chosen arbitrarily one of them.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Numerical bifurcation analysis</head><p>We recall that we are interested in visual hallucinations which are stable solutions of (1) and exist in fairly large regions of the parameter space. The equivariant branching lemma (EBL) provided a set of stationary solutions of (1) for a constant external current I ext = 0. It relies on the Lyapunov-Schmidt reduction (or more generally on the existence of a center manifold) which is local by essence, i.e. valid in a given neighborhood of (0, γ n ) in F × R. The size of this neighborhood quantifies the predictability of the local theory and is bounded by min</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">(|γ n+1 -γ n |, |γ n-1 -γ n |).</formula><p>Hence, for large cortices, it is vanishingly small. We thus use numerical bifurcation analysis to assess our theoretical predictions beyond their above domain of validity. We present some numerical results concerning the equilibria of (1) for a constant external current I ext = 0 as functions of different parameters. Because of the volume of data required to explore the full four-dimensional model (2 dimensions in space and 2 in color) we restrict ourselves to a one-dimensional color space by considering a diameter of the unit disc determined by its hue angle ϕ 0 (between 0 and 1 to be consistent with our notations). A point on this diameter is characterized by its polar coordinates (2πϕ 0 , ρ) or (2π(ϕ 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">+ 1 2 mod 1), ρ), ρ ∈ [0, 1]. The relevant color coordinate is therefore c := ±ρ ∈ [-1, 1].</formula><p>Note that the problem associated has now the symmetry group (D 4 +T 2 ) × Z 2 instead of (D 4 +T 2 ) × O(2). This has been extensively studied <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">55]</ref>. A key remark is that the additional reflection symmetry has no effect on the bifurcation problems associated with the square lattice <ref type="foot" target="#foot_6">6</ref> .</p><p>In the first bifurcation diagram (Section 7.4), we observe that the type of the bifurcated branches and their stability predicted by the EBL are valid outside the neighborhood for the first bifurcation point, of dimension 4. The second bifurcation point, of dimension 8, however provides an example of a branch which becomes stable. Additionally, all stable patterns are alike (stripes) and in agreement with the EBL predictions.</p><p>In the second bifurcation diagram (Section 7.5), we switched the bifurcation points, forcing the first one to be of dimension 8, in hope to see new stationary states, not like stripes. As before, only the stripes are stable and the EBL predictive power, outside the neighborhood, is good.</p><p>In search for more interesting hallucinations and based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[65]</ref>, we changed the criticality of the bifurcation points in the third bifurcation diagram (Section 7.6) hoping to stabilize the patterns with the creation of fold bifurcations. The EBL predictions concerning the stability of the branches are challenged very quickly. In passing, this provides an example of stable spots. Additionally, the bistability between the state V = 0 and the branch of stripes suggests snaking branches. These snaking branches are very interesting because they give birth to stable spatially localized visual hallucinations. The last bifurcation diagram shown in Section 7.7 is dedicated to finding snaking branches.</p><p>To conclude, it seems that we can rely on the EBL to predict the existence of patterns that survive in large parameter domains but not to predict their stability. From the simulations, it seems that the spatial structure of the solutions does not vary much along the branches and this suggests the possibility to extend the results from <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[51]</ref> to the present setting. If such result were true, it would imply that the EBL is a very valuable tool at elucidating the spatial structure of the visual hallucinations. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1.">Color representation of the equilibria of (1)</head><p>The equilibria of (1) are represented by a color image in a way similar to what is described in Section 6. In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>-Left, we show an example of such an equilibrium V eq (r 1 , r 2 , c) where we plot some of its level sets in the three-dimensional space of coordinates (r 1 , r 2 , c). To determine the color represented at cortical location (r 1 , r 2 ), and produce the image in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>-Middle, we compute c(r 1 , r 2 ) = argmax c Υ V eq (r 1 , r 2 , c) ∈ [-1, 1] (corresponding to the maximum activity of the neural mass with spatial coordinates (r 1 , r 2 )) and define the Luminance to be the corresponding activity level a(r 1 , r 2 ) := Υ V eq (r 1 , r 2 , c(r 1 , r 2 )) . In case there are several argmax, we arbitrarily select one of them as in Section 6. At each cortical location (r 1 , r 2 ) we display the color using the HSL color space, see Appendix A and <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[37]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">   H = 2πϕ 0 + π 2 × (1 -sign(c(r 1 , r 2 ))) S = |c(r 1 , r 2 )| L = a(r 1 , r 2 ) (37) where sign(x) = +1 if x ≥ 0 -1 otherwise</formula><p>and obtain the result shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>-Middle. ϕ 0 = 1 8 is defined in Appendix A. Remark 21. Note that this way of displaying our results is a severe simplification of our model which says that at every location (r 1 , r 2 ) in the cortex, color is represented by the function c → Υ(V eq (r 1 , r 2 , c)) and not by the three numbers <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(37)</ref>, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[40]</ref> for an interesting discussion of these issues and much more.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Remark 22.</head><p>The visual cortex of several species (like monkeys) has the property of being retinotopically organized, e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[48,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">53]</ref>. That is, there is a one-to-one mapping from retinal coordinates to cortical ones, the mapping in humans being approximately log polar. Thus, we need to apply an inverse log polar transform to the equilibrium shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>-Middle in V1 coordinates to obtain the result shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>-Right in retinal coordinates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.">Connectivity functions</head><p>In all subsequent examples, we use the following spatial connectivity function w s (r ) of the form (4) whose parameters µ s , ν s and β s are chosen so that it satisfies (5):</p><formula xml:id="formula_87">w s (r ) = A µ s e -r 2 2 /2π 2 -ν s e -r 2 2 /2(β s π) 2 1 r ≤B .<label>(38)</label></formula><p>C. R. Mathématique -0000, 1, n 0, 000-000 2.9 1.9 3π 9</p><p>The set Ω s is the open square (-20π, -20π) 2 . The specific values of these parameters corresponding to different numerical experiments are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">3</ref>. A cross-section is shown in Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref>  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.">Numerical experiments</head><p>All numerical computations were performed in the Julia programming language (version 1.4.2). The bifurcation diagrams were computed using a pseudo-arclength continuation method implemented in the package BifurcationKit.jl <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[63]</ref> with version v0.1.2. The continuation is based on a Newton-Krylov method to solve <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> with GMRES linear solver <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. The computation of the eigen-elements, to detect the bifurcation points, is based on the Arnoldi algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[52]</ref>. The linear and eigen solvers are both implemented in the package KrylovKit.jl. The nonlinear equations <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> were solved at tolerance 10 -11 in the supremum norm. The bifurcation points were located using a bisection algorithm (on the number of unstable eigenvalues) leading to a precision of 10 -4 on the value of the parameter γ, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>.</p><p>Olivier D. Faugeras, Anna Song and Romain</p><p>Let us describe how ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_22">13</ref>) is implemented. The connectivity kernels were computed with the three-dimensional Fast Fourier Transform (3D FFT) on Graphics Processing Units (GPU) based on the package CUDA.jl (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>).</p><p>In order to compute the bifurcating branches, the reduced equations (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref> or proof of Theorem 18) at the bifurcation point were computed thereby yielding a system of polynomial equations of degree 3 in a number of variables equal to the dimension of the kernel of the Jacobian. The roots of these polynomial equations were then computed and used as guesses for points on the bifurcated branches which were corrected using a Deflated-Krylov-Newton (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref>) to prevent converging to the trivial solution. This provides an entirely automatic procedure to find the bifurcated branches at a bifurcation point of any dimension. We call this procedure automatic branch switching (aBS).</p><p>The whole program runs entirely on GPU, a V100 Nvidia card with 32Gb of RAM. The computations are next to impossible to run without a GPU albeit perhaps on a cluster. In the experiments, we use the values N r 1 = N r 2 = 256, N c = 64. Using a finer discretisation would have helped but we were limited by memory when computing eigen elements. Indeed, computing the branches without stability is a matter of a few minutes. However, we found necessary to use a Krylov Space of size ≈ 100, due to the symmetries, in order to compute the eigenvalues, and this limited the size N r 1 × N r 2 × N c of the discretisation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.">First bifurcation diagram</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref> represents the variation of the equilibria (represented by their L 1 norm) as functions of the slope γ of the activation function Υ, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>. The trivial equilibrium V = 0 loses stability at a first bifurcation point around γ ≈ 9.78. The dimension of the first primary bifurcation point is four whereas the dimension of the second one is eight. Given the symmetries of the network, it is straightforward to conclude that the first primary bifurcation is a Pitchfork with D 4 symmetry group.</p><p>Using the aBS procedure (see Section 7.3), we computed the different bifurcating branches from the first two primary bifurcation points. We know that two branches (at most) bifurcate from the first point: one branch of stable stripes (the blue thick line) and one branch of unstable spots (the blue thin line). At the 8D primary bifurcation point, we found four branches with patterns in agreement with the ones described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref>.</p><p>We also computed the bifurcated branches (shown in yellow and brown) from the secondary bifurcation point on the spot branch (in light blue) hoping to find new stable patterns.</p><p>This diagram hints at the fact that only the stripes are stable. At the bottom of Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref> we display the images in cortical coordinates corresponding to some of the equilibria shown in the plot at the top of the Figure . The images are embedded in a frame the same color as the curve on which the corresponding equilibrium sits. A black star has been added to the two images corresponding to the two equilibria (also marked with a black star) sitting on the line of equilibria branching out of the line of unstable spots (thin light blue).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5.">Second bifurcation diagram</head><p>Next, we modified a bit the connectivity to make the dimension of the first bifurcation point 8 and that of the second one 4. We did this hoping to find more interesting stable patterns than in the previous diagram. Using aBS (see Section 7.3), we computed the different bifurcating branches from the bifurcation points. Again, only the stripes were found to be stable. The bifurcated patterns from the 8D bifurcation point are in agreement with the ones referenced in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref>. In fact, the first two bifurcation diagrams collectively show all the possible patterns that can bifurcate from an 8D bifurcation point.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.6.">Third bifurcation diagram, changing the criticality</head><p>We then changed the criticality of the bifurcation points hoping to induce new stable equilibria.</p><p>To this end, we used the following observation. The normal form of the 4D bifurcation point is <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[33]</ref> ż1</p><formula xml:id="formula_88">= z 1 α + β 1 |z 1 | 2 + β 2 |z 2 | 2 ż2 = z 2 α + β 1 |z 2 | 2 + β 2 |z 1 | 2</formula><p>where z i ∈ C, α, β i ∈ R, i = 1, 2, and (for example for β 1 , see <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[62]</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_89">β 1 /γ 3 0 λ 0 = γ 1 s 2 2 A + s 3 /2</formula><p>C. R. Mathématique -0000, 1, n 0, 000-000 where A ∈ R, s 2 = Sig (2) (-ε), s 3 = Sig (3) (-ε), γ 0 is the value of γ at the bifurcation point and λ 0 is the associated eigenvalue of W . We recall that for a threshold ε = 0, s 2 = 0, s 3 &lt; 0 and thus the Pitchfork is supercritical. When varying the threshold ε, the ratio s 3 Using this procedure, we obtain the bifurcation diagram shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">10</ref>. We observe that all primary branches bifurcate sub-critically and thus present a saddle-node bifurcation as proved in <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[65]</ref>. The first two bifurcation points are 4D and 8D, respectively. The stripes branches (red or light brown) from either bifurcation points become stable after the saddlenode bifurcation. Remarkably, the spots branch (blue) from the first 4D bifurcation point is stable close to its saddle-node bifurcation. Using aBS, we find a connection (in violet) between the spot branch and the stripe branch.</p><p>A very similar situation was found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[59]</ref> for the Selkov-Schnakenberg model. The fact that there is bistability between the trivial solution and the stripes (or spots) in a gradient system such as (1) (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[62]</ref> for a proof) opens the doors for the existence of localized patterns and in particular snaking (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[39]</ref> for a review) of localized solutions.</p><p>Snaking is interesting in the context of visual hallucinations because it produces spatially localized possibly stable patterns. These snaking branches usually originate from the bifurcation points on the stripes (resp. spots) branch. We thus computed the secondary branches on the spots branch and show one of them (in green). The green branch connects two bifurcation points on the stripes branch. It consists of localized stripes as seen in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">10</ref>. Unfortunately, it is neither stable nor does it feature snaking. We come back to this point in the next section. Finally, we also computed a secondary branch (in brown) from the branch of spots (primary branch of the 8D bifurcation point). It shows another type of (unstable) localized patterns of spots.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.7.">Fourth bifurcation diagram, snaking branch of localized solutions</head><p>In this last example, we focus on finding snaking branches for <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>. Theoretical analysis (one of the earliest is <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>) shows that snaking occurs in a region which is exponentially small in = γ 1 -γ SN   1   where γ 1 is the value of γ at the 4D bifurcation point and γ SN 1 is that at the location of the saddle-node bifurcation point on the branch of stripes. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[59]</ref> the authors study this behaviour numerically. Thus, to observe snaking, we have to increase ε. By performing codim 2 continuation of the saddle-node bifurcation and the first primary bifurcation point in the (γ, ε) plane, we were able to select a better value of the threshold ε than in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">10</ref>.</p><p>We show the results in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">11</ref> where we have a snaking branch (in green) of solutions arising from a 4D bifurcation point on the branch of stripes (in red). We observe that the localization of the pattern is perpendicular to the stripes. Interestingly, there is another branch (data not shown) of patterns where the localization occurs perpendicular to the stripes and the branch does not snake as explained in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Conclusion</head><p>We have studied some aspects of the bifurcations of the solutions to the neural-field equations describing a model of the primary visual area V1. We had proposed a variant of this model in <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57]</ref> and validated its predictions with some psychovisual data. Here we have focused on the stationary solutions to our equations and their bifurcations which we loosely interpreted as being possible metaphors of visual hallucinations. Visual hallucinations in color are not very well documented in the literature and it is therefore very difficult to compare our model predictions with experimental observations. The closest work to ours is described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and several of the follow-up papers. In these authors' work there was no attempt to model color perception, the focus was on achromatic (i.e. black and white) vision and the interplay between space and edges (borders of objects in the scene) orientations. Like us they studied the bifurcations of the solutions to the neural field equations describing their model and proposed to interpret them as accounting for visual hallucinations. Just like ours, theirs was a rather loose metaphor.</p><p>Going into the mathematics behind the model, we have established here and in <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">65]</ref> the well-posedness of this class of equations whose solutions are defined on a four-dimensional compact spatio-chromatic space representing part of the cortical organisation of the visual cortex. The group of symmetries that acts on this space arises naturally from its spatial extension (assumed to be a square) and the psychophysics of Hering's color perception theory that emphasizes the symmetry with respect to the origin in chromaticity space (corresponding to what is known as opponent colors). Our model equations are equivariant w.r.t. to this spatio-chromatic group and, by identifying some of its axial subgroups we have been able to prove using the equivariant branching lemma that the simplest stationary solution (which turns out to be 0) bifurcates at pitchforks from which arise branches of stationary solutions enjoying the symmetries of the corresponding axial subgroup. be thought of as the product of a luminance axis with a 2D opponent chromaticity space which is assumed to be a disc of radius one centered at the origin. There are many possible choices for the details of such space. For convenience we have adopted the HSL space for Hue, Saturation and Luminance <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[37]</ref>. The (Hue, Saturation) coordinates are precisely the polar coordinates in the 2D chromaticity space, 2πϕ is the polar angle, varying between 0 and 2π since ϕ varies between 0 and 1, and ρ is the distance to the origin, varying between 0 and 1. In Section 7 for minimizing computer memory we restrict ourselves to a diameter of the unit disc, i.e. ϕ := ϕ 0 = 1 8 . The conversion from the HSL space to the usual RGB space is nonlinear and can be found in textbooks such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">69]</ref>.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .Remark 3 .Remark 4 .</head><label>134</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Plot of w c,a (ϕ) defined in (8) for the values of the parameters α c = 0.3, β c = 0.4, µ c = 0.6 and ν c = 0.69.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,123.31,168.88,297.64,196.89" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Theorem 18 .</head><label>18</label><figDesc>Let us denote by (λ n ) the eigenvalues of W ∈ L (L 2 (Ω)) and γ n := 1 Sig (-ε)λ n the bifurcation points. The smooth G -equivariant mapping F : W m,2 (Ω) × R → L 2 (Ω) satisfies the assumptions of the equivariant branching lemma. For each axial subgroup Σ ⊂ G shown in Table</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. An example of a planform whose equation is given by (33): Left in cortical coordinates, Right in retinal coordinates.</figDesc><graphic coords="16,31.81,281.31,238.11,158.74" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. An example of a planform whose equation is given by (34): Left in cortical coordinates, Right in retinal coordinates.</figDesc><graphic coords="16,274.33,281.31,238.11,158.74" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. An example of a planform whose equation is (35): Left in cortical coordinates, Right in retinal coordinates.</figDesc><graphic coords="17,274.33,281.39,238.11,158.74" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. An example of a planform whose equation is (36): Left in cortical coordinates, Right in retinal coordinates.</figDesc><graphic coords="17,31.81,281.39,238.11,158.74" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. Left: example of level sets of an equilibrium, a stationary solution, of (1). Middle: Color image representation of the equilibrium shown on the left. Right: Same as Middle but in retinal coordinates.</figDesc><graphic coords="19,83.62,76.29,121.94,114.11" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>-Left: it has the "traditional" Mexican hat shape.Similarly w c (c, c ) is defined byw c (c, c ) := µ c e -α c |c-c | -ν c e -β c |c+c |with the following values of the parameters: α c = 0.3 β c = 0.4 µ c = 0.6, ν c = 0.69. The set Ω c is the open interval (-1, 1). A heatmap of this function is shown in Figure 7-Right. a.u. a.u.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure Left: Typical shape of the spatial connectivity w s used in the numerical experiments. Right: Heatmap plot of the color connectivity function w c (c, c ) used in the numerical experiments.</figDesc><graphic coords="20,284.63,332.64,153.14,114.01" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>1 Figure 8 .</head><label>18</label><figDesc>Figure 8. First bifurcation diagram: Equilibria are shown as functions of the nonlinear gain γ in cortical coordinates. The values of the parameters are shown in Table 3. The stable parts of the branches are indicated with thick lines. The dots indicate bifurcation points. Only the first two primary bifurcation points are shown. The colours around the images are those of the corresponding branches. The first seven images represent the intersections of the vertical black line with the bifurcated branches. The last two images correspond to the two black stars in the bifurcation diagram.</figDesc><graphic coords="22,146.30,473.49,83.69,84.27" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9. Second bifurcation diagram: Equilibria are shown as functions of the nonlinear gain γ in cortical coordinates. The values of the parameters are shown in Table 3. The stable parts of the branches are indicated with thick lines. The dots indicate bifurcation points. Only the first three primary bifurcation points are shown. As in Figure 8 the colours surrounding the images correspond to those of the branches found at the intersections of the bifurcated curves with the vertical black line.</figDesc><graphic coords="23,241.19,381.18,83.33,83.22" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10. Third bifurcation diagram: Equilibria are shown as function of the nonlinear gain γ in cortical coordinates. The values of the parameters are shown in Table 3. The stable parts of the branches are indicated with thick lines. The dots indicate bifurcation points. Only the first three primary bifurcation points are shown. The colour surrounding the image is that of its corresponding branch. Their location on the bifurcation diagram is shown with a black star.</figDesc><graphic coords="24,150.67,477.30,80.71,80.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>s 2 2 takes</head><label>2</label><figDesc>on any value, thus we can change the criticality by altering the threshold. Compared to the previous diagram, we used ε = 2.3 and scaled the connectivity to restrict the value of γ at the first bifurcation point.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11. Fourth bifurcation diagram: Equilibria are shown as functions of the nonlinear gain γ in cortical coordinates. The values of the parameters are shown in Table 3. The stable parts of the branches are indicated with thick lines. The dots indicate bifurcation points. Only the first three primary bifurcation points are shown. The right part of the Figure shows a zoomed version of the diagram in which the snaking is more apparent. Three images are shown at the bottom of the Figure, corresponding to the black stars in the two diagrams above. The colour surrounding each image corresponds to that of the corresponding branch.</figDesc><graphic coords="26,119.78,245.72,100.39,100.39" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>The axial subgroups Σ of G in dimension 4 and two of them in dimension 8, as well as their corresponding fixed spaces. Each group element is of the form ( , ψ), where ∈ E (L ) is the semi-direct sum of D 4 and T 2 and ψ ∈ O(2). The identity of D 4 (respectively O(</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Parameters used in </figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Bifurcation diagram ε</cell><cell>β s</cell><cell>B</cell><cell>A</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell cols="3">1.9 3π 1.0</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell cols="4">0.5 20.9 6π 1.0</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell cols="4">2.3 1.9 3π 9</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>We do not consider the achromatic component of a color, except for display, see Section 7.1, and restrict ourselves to the chromatic components.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>A neural mass is an aggregate of neurons in which the spatial dimension is ignored, see e.g.<ref type="bibr" target="#b68">[67]</ref>.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_2"><p>More precisely we used instead of V the "activity" variable a = Υ(V ), see the definition (2) of the sigmoid function below. The two formulations are equivalent in the case I ext = 0 considered here.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_3"><p>In mathematical neuroscience this integro-differential equation is often called a Wilson-Cowan equation<ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[68]</ref> C. R. Mathématique -0000, 1, n 0, 000-000</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_4"><p>It is only qualitatively the same as the one in<ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57]</ref>.C. R. Mathématique -0000, 1, n 0, 000-000</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_5"><p>C. R. Mathématique -0000, 1, n 0, 000-000</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_6"><p>This was pointed out to us by Pascal Chossat.C. R. Mathématique -0000, 1, n 0, 000-000</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>The authors thank <rs type="person">Pascal Chossat</rs> for useful discussions. They are also grateful to the OPAL infrastructure from <rs type="institution">Université Côte d'Azur</rs> for providing resources and support. The third author would like to thank <rs type="person">Hannes Uecker</rs> for his fruitful discussions.</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Going into the numerics, the Julia package developed by the third author has allowed us to explore a much larger range of values of the bifurcation parameter than for example the authors of <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> whose approach, based on the use of normal forms, is not well-suited to the analysis of subcritical bifurcations. It has also allowed us to discover cases of snaking and hence to observe stable localised solutions. To our knowledge this is the first time this has been reported in a model of the primary visual area. It raises the fascinating question of whether such spatio-chromatic patterns can be observed in animal or human perception.</p><p>Going further into the numerics, this is to our knowledge the first time that a bifurcation analysis of an infinite dimensional system of integro-differential equations is entirely carried out on GPUs. By considerably reducing the response time of our computer simulations it has allowed us to explore in much greater depth than what had been possible before the complicated structure of the solutions to our model equations with the result that we will in the future be able to better confront our predictions with perceptual experiments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix A. Color space</head><p>It is not important for this work to precisely define the color space we use because the phenomena described in this paper are robust to changes of this definition as long as the color space can C. R. Mathématique -0000, 1, n 0, 000-000</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sobolev spaces</title>
		<title level="s">Pure and Applied Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J F</forename><surname>Fournier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sobolev spaces</title>
		<title level="s">Pure and Applied Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">140</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamics of pattern formation in lateral-inhibition type neural fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-I</forename><surname>Amari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">To snake or not to snake in the planar Swift-Hohenberg equation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Avitabile</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J B</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Burke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Knobloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sandstede</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Appl. Dyn. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="704" to="733" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Templates for the Solution of Linear Systems: Building Blocks for Iterative Methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barrett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Berry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Demmel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Donato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dongarra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Eijkhout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pozo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Romine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Van Der</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Vorst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geometry of color perception. II: Perceived colors from real quantum states and Hering&apos;s rebit</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Berthier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>article no. 14 (25 pages</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid software prototyping for heterogeneous and distributed platforms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Besard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Churavy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Edelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Sutter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Eng. Softw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effective Extensible Programming: Unleashing Julia on GPUs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Besard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Foket</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Sutter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Parallel Distrib. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="827" to="841" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatiotemporal dynamics of continuum neural fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Bressloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. A, Math. Theor</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">33001</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>109 pages</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geometric visual hallucinations, Euclidean symmetry and the functional architecture of striate cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Bressloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cowan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Golubitsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wiener</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond., Ser. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">306</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1407</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="330" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patterns of convection in spherical shells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Busse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Fluid Mech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exponential asymptotics of localised patterns and snaking bifurcation diagrams</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chapman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kozyreff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physica D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">238</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="319" to="354" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chromatic micromaps in primary visual cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chatterjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ohki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Reid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021. 2315</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Solutions avec symétrie diédrale dans les problèmes de bifurcation invariants par symétrie sphérique</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chossat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">C. R. Math. Acad. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">297</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="639" to="642" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Methods in equivariant bifurcations and dynamical systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chossat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lauterbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Advanced Series in Nonlinear Dynamics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>World Scientific</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Steady-state bifurcation with O(3)-symmetry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chossat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lauterbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Melbourne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch. Ration. Mech. Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="376" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Symmetry breakdown from bifurcation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cicogna</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lettere al Nuovo Cimento</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="600" to="602" />
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971. 1985. 1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oculocentric spatial representation in parietal cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Colby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Duhamel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Goldberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cereb. Cortex</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="470" to="481" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tutorial on Neural Field Theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Coombes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Beim Graben</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Potthast</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Neural Fields: Theory and Applications</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Coombes</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Beim Graben</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Potthast</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="43" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mathématique</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">0</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="0" to="000" />
			<date>0000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient codes and balanced networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Denève</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Machens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="375" to="382" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Planforms in two and three dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dionne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Golubitsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Z. Angew. Math. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Time-periodic spatially periodic Planforms in Euclidean equivariant partial differential equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dionne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Golubitsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Silber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Stewart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond., Ser. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">352</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1698</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="168" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stability results for steady, spatially periodic planforms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dionne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Silber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Skeldon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nonlinearity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="353" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neural networks as spatio-temporal pattern-forming systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ermentrout</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rep. Prog. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="353" to="430" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temporal oscillations in neuronal nets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ermentrout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cowan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="280" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deflation Techniques for Finding Distinct Solutions of Nonlinear Partial Differential Equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Farrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Á</forename><surname>Birkisson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Funke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Sci. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2026" to="A2045" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Persistent neural states: stationary localized activity patterns in nonlinear continuous n-population, q-dimensional neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Faugeras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Veltz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Grimbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neural Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="187" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mnemonic coding of visual space in the monkey&apos;s dorsolateral prefrontal cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Funahashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bruce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Goldman-Rakic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="349" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Golubitsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Schaeffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Singularities and Groups in Bifurcation Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">I</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Applied Mathematical Sciences</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Symmetry Perspective. From equilibrium to chaos in phase space and physical space</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Golubitsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Stewart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Progress in Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">200</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<publisher>Birkhäuser</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Golubitsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Stewart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Schaeffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Singularities and Groups in Bifurcation Theory</title>
		<title level="s">Applied Mathematical Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">II</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hering</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Outlines of a theory of the light sense</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1964">1964</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hoyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Pattern formation: an introduction to methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Blobs and color vision</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hubel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Bioscience at the Physical Science Frontier</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="102" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eye, Brain, and Vision</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<publisher>Scientific American Library</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pattern selection with O(3) symmetry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ihrig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Golubitsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physica D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Color Spaces for Computer Graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Joblove</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Greenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM SIGGRAPH Comput. Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Principles of neuroscience</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kandel</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jessell</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Siegelbaum</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hudspeth</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>5th ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial Localization in Dissipative Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Knobloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Rev. Cond. Matter Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="325" to="359" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Koenderink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Color for the Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anatomical Substrates for Functional Columns in Macaque Monkey Primary Visual Cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lund</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Angelucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Bressloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cereb. Cortex</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neural mechanisms of visual working memory in prefrontal cortex of the Macaque</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Erickson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Desimone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5154" to="5167" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Standard definitions of chromatic induction fail to describe induction with S-cone patterned backgrounds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Monnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vision Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2708" to="2714" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chromatic induction from S-cone patterns</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Monnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Shevell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vision Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="849" to="856" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How rare are subgroups of index 2?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Nganou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="220" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effective computation of SO(3) and O(3) linear representation symmetry classes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Olive</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Mech. Compl. Sys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="237" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phosphenes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Oster</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Am</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">222</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Petitot</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Elements of neurogeometry</title>
		<title level="s">Lecture Notes in Morphogenesis</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Existence and properties of solutions for neural field equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Potthast</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Beim Graben</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Methods Appl. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="935" to="949" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geometry of color perception. I: Structures and metrics of a homogeneous color space</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Provenzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>article no. 7 (19 pages</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some global results for nonlinear eigenvalue problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Rabinowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Funct. Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="487" to="513" />
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Numerical methods for large eigenvalue problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Saad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Classics in Applied Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>rev. ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial mapping in the primate sensory projection: Analytic structure and relevance to perception</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="194" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hallucinations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Siegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Am</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">237</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="132" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pattern selection in steady binary-fluid convection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Silber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Knobloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1468" to="1477" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hopf bifurcation on a square lattice</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nonlinearity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1063" to="1107" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A neural field model for color perception unifying assimilation and contrast</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Faugeras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Veltz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1007050</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whither the hypercolumn?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Ts'o</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Zarella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Burkitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">587</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2791" to="2805" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mathématique</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">0</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="0" to="000" />
			<date>0000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Numerical Results for Snaking of Patterns over Patterns in Some 2D Selkov-Schnakenberg Reaction-Diffusion Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Uecker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wetzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Appl. Dyn. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="94" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Local Bifurcation and Symmetry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vanderbauwhede</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Rijksuniversiteit Gent</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD Thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceptual spaces and their symmetries: The geometry of color space</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Vattuone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wachtler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Samengo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://mna.episciences.org/7680" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Neurosci. Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nonlinear analysis methods in neural field models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Veltz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://pastel.archives-ouvertes.fr/tel-00686695" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Université Paris Est</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD Thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-02902346" />
		<title level="m">BifurcationKit.jl</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the Effects on Cortical Spontaneous Activity of the Symmetries of the Network of Pinwheels in Visual Area V1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Veltz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chossat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Faugeras</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>article no. 11 (28 pages</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Local/Global Analysis of the Stationary Solutions of Some Neural Field Equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Veltz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Faugeras</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Appl. Dyn. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="954" to="998" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changes in perceived color due to chromatic interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ware</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Cowan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vision Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1353" to="1362" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Excitatory and inhibitory interactions in localized populations of model neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cowan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A mathematical theory of the functional dynamics of cortical and thalamic nervous tissue</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wyszecki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Stiles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Color Science: Concepts and Methods, Quantitative Data and Formulas</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hue maps in primate striate cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Casti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kaplan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="771" to="786" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mathématique</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">0</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="0" to="000" />
			<date>0000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
